One Pace Premium Keep the project alive: ko-fi.com/not6ip
One Pace Premium Keep the project alive: ko-fi.com/not6ip
Noland the Liar
‫نولاند الكذاب‬
Why? Why? Why?
‫سُحقًا... سُحقًا... سُحقًا...‬
Why? That damn orangutan!
‫سُحقًا... لإنسان الغاب ذاك!‬
He wrecked the ship even more!
‫لقد دمّر السفينة أكثر!‬
This ship really has started to fall apart. Maybe it's about time to replace her?
‫بدأت هذه السفينة تتداعى... ربّما حان الوقت لاستبدالها؟‬
Don't you dare start saying careless things too!
‫إيّاك أن تجرؤ على قول أشياء غير مراعية كهذه أنت أيضًا!‬
Don't you dare!
‫أنت أيضًا!‬
We get it, Usopp. There's no need to worry.
‫أعلم يا أوسوب، لن تفيدنا الشّكوى بأيّ شيء‬
The Going Merry is a special part of the team.
‫غوينغ ميري رفيق قيّم لنا،‬
Don't you dare!
‫تعرف تمامًا!...‬
You...! You...!
‫تعرف... تعرف...‬
So let's work hard and repair the ship!
‫لذلك دعنا نعمل بجدّ ونصلح هذه السفينة!‬
We...! We get... get... get it!
‫تمامًا كيف... تمامًا كيف... تمامًا كيف!...‬
Luffy, you're such...
‫لوفي... إنّك فعلًا...‬
...an oaf!
‫أيّها الأحمق!‬
To go east from Mock Town, we needed to circle around the island.
‫غادرنا موكتاون واتّجهنا شرقًا عن طريق دوراننا حول الجزيرة‬
We'll reach the spot on the map soon.
‫سنصل إلى الموقع المحدد على الخريطة قريبًا‬
That's where that guy... What's his name again?
‫ما كان اسم ذلك الرجل؟‬
Mont Blanc Cricket.
‫مونبلان كريكت.‬
So that guy who talks about his big dreams lives there?
‫إذًا فالرّجل الّذي يتحدّث عن الأحلام هناك، صحيح؟‬
A-Amazing!
‫هـ-هذا مذهل!‬
He lives there?! Isn't that a palace?!
‫هذا منزله؟! إنّه قصر!‬
Is this Mont Blanc Cricket guy loaded?!
‫هل مونبلان كريكت هذا فاحش الثّراء؟!‬
Idiots! Look closer.
‫غبيّان! أمعنا النّظر‬
A dreamer, huh?
‫حالم؟ يبدو لي ساعيًا لجلب الانتباه‬
Why?
‫لماذا؟‬
What the...?! It's just a board?!
‫ماذا؟! إنّه مجّرد لوح!‬
What?!
‫ماذا؟!‬
There's only half a house. The rest is just a veneer.
‫المنزل الحقيقيّ هو نصفه فحسب، الباقي مجرّد مظاهر خادعة‬
He's probably a stingy guy.
‫يبدو لي رجلًا رخيصًا‬
What kind of dreams did he talk about to get driven out of town?
‫أيّ نوع من الأحلام الّتي تحدّث عنها أدّت به ليُنفى من البلدة؟‬
I'm not sure of the details,
‫لا أدري ما التّفاصيل،‬
but apparently he claimed that a lot of gold is hidden away in Jaya.
‫لكنّني سمعتُ أنّه قال أنّ مقدارًا هائلًا من الذّهب موجود في جايا‬
Gold?!
‫الذّهب؟!‬
Did some pirate bury treasure here or what?
‫أهو كنز قراصنة مدفون أو ما شابه؟‬
Well, I don't know.
‫أنا لا أدري‬
Gold!
‫ذهب!‬
Dig it up, Chopper! Find the gold!
‫احفر الأرض يا تشوبر! سنجد الذّهب!‬
We'll find it by digging?
‫سنجده إن حفرت؟‬
So he lives alone way out here?
‫أيعيش وحده في هذا المكان المنعزل؟‬
Hello. I'm coming in.
‫مرحبًا... أستأذن للدّخول‬
Can't you wait a minute?!
‫ألم تستطع الانتظار قليلًا؟!‬
Huh? No one's here.
‫لا أحد هنا‬
Hello?!
‫مرحبًا؟!‬
No answer.
‫لم يجب أحد‬
Wait, you idiot! What if this guy's dangerous?
‫انتظر أيّها الغبيّ! ما الّذي ستفعله إن كان هذا الرّجل خطيرًا؟‬
Hey, guys! No one's home!
‫يا رفاق! لا أحد هنا!‬
This is...
‫هذا...‬
a picture book.
‫كتاب صور...‬
It's quite an old book.
‫إنّه كتاب قديم جدًّا‬
It's titled "Noland the Liar."
‫عنوانه «نولاند الكذاب»‬
Wow, what a cool title! That's a great idea for a book!
‫نعم، إنّه عنوان رائع! فكرة ممتازة لكتاب!‬
"Noland the Liar"?
‫«نولاند الكذاب»؟‬
You know it, Sanji?
‫أتعرفه يا سانجي-كن؟‬
But it says it was published in the North Blue.
‫لكن مكتوب أنه نُشِر في الأزرق الشمالي‬
Yeah. I was born in the North Blue.
‫نعم، وُلدت في الأزرق الشمالي‬
I've never told you guys, huh?
‫ألم أخبركم بهذا قبلًا؟‬
That's news to me.
‫هذا جديد علي، ظننتُك من الشرقي مثلنا‬
I only grew up there.
‫ترعرعت هناك فحسب‬
Quiet, Chopper! What are you doing?!
‫اهدأ يا تشوبر! ما الّذي تفعله؟!‬
What?!
‫ماذا؟!‬
This story is well-known in the North.
‫هذه قصّة مشهورة في الشّمال‬
It's a children's story,
‫إنّها قصّة خياليّة،‬
but I've heard that this Noland guy really existed once upon a time.
‫لكن سمعتُ أنّ نولاند هذا عاش حقًّا قبل زمن بعيد‬
This is a story from long, long ago—
‫كان يا ما كان في غابر الزمان،‬
a story that dates back 400 years.
‫قصة تعود أحداثها لأربعمئة عام من الآن‬
Somewhere in the North Blue,
‫لرجل يُدعى مونبلان نولاند من بلادٍ في الأزرق الشمالي‬
Noland was an explorer who always spoke of his fantastical adventures.
‫كان نولاند مكتشفًا كثير الحديث عن مغامراته المدهشة‬
However, the villagers couldn't tell if his stories were true or not.
‫ولكن القرويّون لم يكن بوسعهم معرفة صحّة تلك القصص من عدمها‬
After returning from an expedition, Noland reported to the king:
‫وذات يوم، ذهب للقاء الملك بعد عودته من ترحاله وقال له:‬
"I saw a mountain of gold on an island in the great sea."
‫«رأيتُ جبل ذهب على جزيرة في البحر العظيم»‬
The brave king set sail to the great sea
‫أبحر الملك الشّجاع إلى البحر العظيم...‬
to find out if the story was true, taking 2,000 soldiers along with him.
‫ليرى إن كانت القصّة حقيقيّة، آخذًا معه ألفَيْ جنديّ‬
After weathering large storms and battling sea beasts,
‫بعد نجاتهم من عواصف عظيمة ومقاتلتهم لوحوش كثيرة،‬
only 100 soldiers, the king, and Noland arrived at the island.
‫لم يصل منهم سوى الملك ونولاند ومئة جنديّ فحسب للجزيرة‬
However, all they found there was an ordinary jungle.
‫ولكن، ما وجدوه كان مجرّد غابة‬
In the end, he was sentenced to death for the crime of lying.
‫في النّهاية، حُكم على نولاند بالموت لقاء جريمة الكذب‬
Noland's last words were:
‫وقد كانت كلمات نولاند الأخيرة كالتّالي:‬
"That's it! The mountain of gold sank into the sea!"
‫«هذا صحيح! غرق جبل الذّهب عميقًا في البحر»‬
The king and his people were dumbfounded.
‫كان الملك والآخرون مصدومين‬
No one believed Noland anymore.
‫لم يصدّق أحد نولاند بعد ذلك‬
Until his dying breath, Noland continued to lie.
‫لأنّه واصل كذبه حتّى لحظة مماته‬
This book is based on the North Blue tale "Noland the Liar."
‫عن قصص «نولاند الكذّاب» من الأزرق الشّماليّ الخياليّة‬
Mock Town, Jaya
‫موكتاون، جايا‬
Mont Blanc Cricket is a descendant of that Mont Blanc Noland?!
‫مونبلان كريكت خليفة لمونبلان نولاند ذاك؟!‬
I heard that story a lot when I was a kid.
‫سمعتُ تلك القصّة الخياليّة عندما كنتُ طفلًا‬
There isn't anyone in the North Blue who doesn't know that tale.
‫لا يوجد من في الأزرق الشّماليّ لا يعرفها‬
We're all from the North Blue, so we often got told
‫جميعنا من الأزرق الشّماليّ لذلك قِيل لنا كثيرًا...‬
that if we lied a lot, we'd be sentenced to death like Noland.
‫أنّنا إن كذبنا كثيرًا، فسيُحكم علينا بالموت مثل نولاند‬
This is getting even more interesting!
‫يصبح هذا ممتعًا أكثر فأكثر!‬
I'd never have guessed the island in that children's tale was Jaya.
‫ما كنتُ لأتخيّل أبدًا أنّ جايا هي الجزيرة المذكورة في القصّة‬
And after 400 years, Noland the Liar's descendant
‫وبعد أربعمئة سنة، يبحث سليل نولاند الكذّاب‬
is looking for the gold on this island, huh?
‫عن الذّهب في هذه الجزيرة إذًا‬
All to clear the name of a lying ancestor who was a joke until he died.
‫بغاية تبرئة اسم سلفه الّذي نُعت بالكذاب وسُخر منه حتى مات‬
This family cracks me up!
‫يا لها من عشيرة مضحكة!‬
Does he really think he can clear the name
‫هل يعتقد فعلًا أنّ بإمكانه تبرئة‬
of his 400-year-old ancestor by bringing back a bit of gold?!
‫اسم سلف له منذ أربعمئة سنة بالعثور على بعض الذّهب؟!‬
Sounds like he has a few screws loose!
‫يبدو أنّه مخبول!‬
Unfortunately for the liar, he died...
‫وللأسف، مات الكذّاب...‬
before he could ever become a brave warrior of the sea.
‫قبل حتّى أن يصبح محارب بحر شجاع!‬
Don't look at me!
‫لا تنظري إليّ!‬
And don't go adding a tragic sentence of your own!
‫ولا تضيفي جملًا مفجعة من تلقاء نفسك!‬
Luffy fell into the sea!
‫وقع لوفي في البحر!‬
What are you doing?!
‫ما الّذي تفعله؟!‬
Who the hell are you?!
‫من تكونون؟!‬
You've got guts relaxing uninvited
‫يا لجرأتكم وأنتم تسترخون في منزل غيركم دون إذن!‬
Pirate Mont Blanc Cricket Saruyama Alliance's Last Boss
‫القرصان «مونبلان كريكت»‬ ‫أحد قادة تحالف ساروياما‬
These are my waters!
‫هذا الجزء من البحر ضمن منطقتي!‬
Hey, Usopp! Go grab Luffy!
‫اذهب لإخراج لوفي يا أوسوب‬
Okay!
‫حسنًا!‬
You're after the gold, aren't you? Time to die!
‫تسعون خلف الذّهب، صحيح؟ مت!‬
– Sanji!
‫سانجي!‬
Don't worry. It didn't hit me.
‫لا تقلقا. لم تصبني‬
Hold on!
‫تمهّل!‬
Idiot. Don't underestimate your opponent.
‫غبيّ، لا يجب عليك الاستخفاف بخصمك‬
Move! I'll handle this!
‫ابتعد! سأهتمّ بأمره!‬
Hey, what were you doing?!
‫مهلًا، ماذا كنتَ تفعل؟!‬
I saw bubbles coming out of the water.
‫رأيت فقاعات تخرج من الماء‬
So I went to check it out, and then a chestnut appeared.
‫لذلك كنتُ أنظر للماء، ثمّ ظهرت حبّة كستناء فجأة‬
But the chestnut was actually a guy, and he dragged me into the water.
‫لكنّ حبّة الكستناء كانت في الحقيقة رجلًا، ثمّ قام بسحبي إلى المياه‬
Hey, it's you!
‫مهلًا، أيّها العم!‬
Bring more cold towels! Open up the windows!
‫أحضروا المزيد من المناشف الباردة! افتحوا النّوافذ!‬
Divers' disease?
‫مرض تخفيف الضّغط؟‬
Is this guy sick?
‫هل هذا الرّجل مريض؟‬
Yeah, it's a sickness that divers sometimes get.
‫نعم، مرض يصيب الغطّاسين أحيانًا‬
It doesn't usually develop into a chronic condition though.
‫لكنّها لا تصبح حالة مُزمنة عادةً‬
Due to a lack of decompression when surfacing from the seabed,
‫انخفاض الضّغط السريع عند الصّعود لسطح البحر من أعماقه،‬
nitrogen dissolved in the blood is released fast and forms gas bubbles.
‫يُحّرر النيتروجين المتحلّل في الدّم بسرعة ويشكّل فقاعات غازيّة حينها‬
Since gas bubbles expand inside and outside of blood vessels,
‫وبما أنّ فقاعات الغاز تتوسّع داخل وخارج الأوعية الدّمويّة،‬
they can cause blood flow, muscle, and joint problems.
‫تتسبّب بمشكلات في تدفّق الدّم والعضلات والمفاصل‬
So it's a weird mystery, huh?
‫أي أنّها ظاهرة غامضة من نوع ما؟‬
He probably kept diving every day without taking time
‫على الأرجح أنّه واصل الغوص كلّ يوم‬
for those bubbles to dissipate from his body.
‫دون منح الفرصة للفقاعات بالاختفاء من جسده‬
What for?!
‫ولكن لأيّ سبب؟!‬
I don't know, but it's dangerous.
‫لا أدري، لكنّه يخاطر بحياته‬
In some cases, divers' sickness can...
‫في بعض الحالات، يمكن لمرض تخفيف الضّغط...‬
cause death.
‫أن يسبّب الموت‬
Oh hey, it's you, Masira. So you're alive.
‫هذا أنت يا ماسيرا. أنت حيّ إذًا!‬
Alive? What are you talking about?
‫حيّ؟ عمّ تتحدّث؟‬
Never mind. What was that gunfire about, anyway?
‫لا تهتمّ. على كلّ حال، ما كان إطلاق النّار ذاك؟‬
Yeah, brother! Do you think something's up with the boss?
‫صحيح يا أخي! هل تعتقد أنّ شيئًا ما حدث للعجوز؟‬
Let's hurry! I'm getting worried!
‫لنسرع! بدأت أقلق!‬
– Boss! Are you all right?!
‫أيّها العجوز! هل أنت بخير؟!‬
They've come to kill us!
‫سيقتلاننا!‬
What are you guys doing here?!
‫ما الّذي تفعلونه هنا؟!‬
What did you do to the boss?!
‫ما الّذي فعلتموه للعجوز؟!‬
Huh? We're helping this guy right now, so go away.
‫ماذا؟ نحن نعتني بهذا الرّجل الآن لذلك اذهبا لمكان آخر‬
Dummy! They aren't going to listen to reason!
‫غبيّ! لن يستمعا لنا أبدًا!‬
They're savages, you know!
‫إنّهما متوحّشان تمامًا!‬
You know!
‫تمامًا!‬
Everyone, jump through the windows!
‫لنخلِ المكان جميعًا عبر النّوافذ!‬
– You...
‫أنتم...‬
– people are so nice!
‫أنتم لطفاء جدًّا!‬
They're listening!
‫استمعا لنا فعلًا!‬
You guys live here, too?
‫تعيشان هنا أيضًا؟‬
Well, the house the boss lives in is the Saruyama Alliance's headquarters.
‫في الواقع، منزل العجوز هو مقرّ تحالف ساروياما‬
But we sleep on our ships most of the time
‫لكنّنا ننام في سفننا معظم الوقت‬
because this house is too cramped for us.
‫لأنّ هذا المنزل صغير جدًّا علينا‬
It's because you guys are too big.
‫هذا لأنّكما ضخمان للغاية‬
But compared to those giants, you look like clumps of earwax.
‫لكن مقارنة بالعمالقة، فأنتما تبدوان ككتل صملاخ أذن‬
Why are they getting along so well?
‫لماذا هم على وفاق تامّ هكذا؟‬
I guess they've got a lot in common.
‫ربّما لأنّ لديهم الكثير من الأمور المشتركة‬
But it's amazing how you punted him so far when you're all so small!
‫لكن من المدهش أنّكم استطعتم ركله رغم صغر حجمكم!‬
Oh? You could do it too.
‫فعلًا؟ بإمكانك ذلك أيضًا‬
You think so?
‫فعلًا؟‬
Yup. It comes with being a monkey.
‫نعم، بإمكانك ذلك بما أنك قرد‬
Luffy, he's come around!
‫لوفي، لقد استفاق!‬
He's awake?!
‫استيقظ؟!‬
Hey, he's right. Masira went flying.
‫إنّه محقّ، بإمكاني ركل ماسيرا‬
Hey, chestnut head! I wanna ask you something!
‫أيّها العمّ ذو الرّأس الماسيّ! أريد سؤالك عن شيء ما!‬
Sorry I caused you trouble.
‫أعتذر عن تسبّبي بالمتاعب لكم‬
I thought you were just more jerks after the gold.
‫ظننتُكم مجرّد أغبياء يسعون خلف الذّهب‬
What?! You have gold?
‫ماذا؟! ألديك ذهب؟!‬
Don't you dare.
‫لا تسعي خلفها.‬
What is it that you want to ask me?
‫ما الّذي أردت أن تسألني عنه؟‬
We wanna go to the sky island! Please tell us how to get there!
‫أيّها العمّ، نريد الذهاب لجزيرة السماء، أخبرنا بكيفية الذهاب إليها!‬
Sky island?
‫جزيرة السماء؟‬
You guys believe in the sky island?
‫أتصدّقون بوجود جزيرة السماء؟‬
Hey, stop it! He's sick!
‫توقّفي! فهو مريض!‬
Isn't there a sky island?!
‫ألا وجود لجزيرة السماء أيها العم؟!‬
No one knows.
‫ومَن قد يعلم؟‬
I know of someone who said there is,
‫أعرف رجلًا قال أنّها موجودة!‬
but everyone came to know him as a big liar,
‫لكن الناس ينعتونه بالكذاب العظيم الأسطوري!‬
and his family turned into a laughingstock.
‫وقد أمست عشيرته محلّ سخرية للأبد!‬
It's not me!
‫ليس أنا!‬
There's a well-known, old story from the North Blue.
‫ثمّة قصّة قديمة يعرفها معظم ساكنة الأزرق الشّماليّ‬
It's called "Noland the Liar."
‫إنها «نولاند الكذاب»‬
Like I said, it's not me! Our names are different, right?!
‫قلتُ لك أنّه ليس أنا! كما أن اسمه مختلف تمامًا!‬
You're related?!
‫هل أنت سليل له؟!‬
Could this place be the island from that story?!
‫وهل هذه هي الجزيرة في تلك القصّة؟!‬
He's my great, great, great...
‫إنّه جدُّ جدِّ جدّي‬
He's a distant ancestor of mine.
‫إنّه سلفي من بعيد، كم هذا مزعج...‬
I doubt there's a drop of his blood in my body.
‫أشكّ أنّه ما زالت في عروقي قطرة دم من دمائه...‬
The Mont Blanc family was driven out of their country and kept a low profile,
‫مع أنّ عائلة مونبلان طُردت من البلاد، ولم تجلب لها الأنظار كثيرًا،‬
yet people continue to denounce our name to this day.
‫إلّا أنّ النّاس واصلوا استنكار عائلتنا ليومنا هذا...‬
But no one in the family hates him.
‫لكنّ لا أحد من العائلة يمقته.‬
Why?
‫لماذا؟‬
Because Noland was an incredibly honest person.
‫لأنّ نولاند كان شخصًا صادقًا بشكل استثنائيّ‬
But in that picture book...
‫لكنّ كتاب الصّور ذاك...‬
Noland's last moment in the picture book was an explanation:
‫كان عُذر نولاند الأخير في ذلك الكتاب على هذا النّحو:‬
"That's it! The mountain of gold sank into the sea!"
‫«هذا صحيح! غرق جبل الذّهب عميقًا في البحر»‬
The book added that dopey facial expression...
‫رُسم وجه تعلوه ملامح الغباء في الكتاب‬
but his tears never stopped, and he died full of regret.
‫لكنّه ذرف دموعًا كثيرة ومات ميتة يملؤها النّدم‬
He was sure that the island they landed on
‫كان واثقًا أنّ الجزيرة الّتي وصل إليها كانت جايا‬
was the same place he found the remains of a City of Gold: Jaya.
‫حيث وجد أطلال مدينة من الذهب‬
He was certain it couldn't possibly be just a hallucination.
‫شعر أنّه كان من المستحيل أنّها كانت مجرّد وهم‬
Noland insisted that the ruins submerged due to tectonic shifts,
‫أصرّ نولاند أنّ الأطلال غرقت بسبب تحرّكات القشرة الأرضيّة،‬
but everyone thought he was making excuses out of desperation.
‫لكنّ الجميع ظنّوا أنّه يختلق أعذارًا بسبب وضعه اليائس‬
Noland was executed in front of the laughing onlookers,
‫أُعدم نولاند أمام الحشود الساخرة،‬
and only the name "Liar" remained.
‫ولم يبقَ سوى لقب «الكذاب»‬
Oh, I see!
‫فهمت!‬
You're looking for the City of Gold to clear the Mont Blanc family's name!
‫إذًا فأنت تبحث عن مدينة الذّهب في قاع البحر‬
Don't be silly!
‫كفاك سخافةً!‬
Usopp!
‫أوسوب!‬
I thought I died...
‫ظننتُني سأموت...‬
How honest my distant ancestor was, or how great an explorer he was,
‫كم كان سلفي صادقًا، أو كم كان مكتشفًا رائعًا،‬
has nothing to do with me!
‫لا علاقة لهما بي!‬
Can you understand how a kid would feel being laughed at by strangers
‫هل يمكنك إدراك كيف سيشعر طفل يسخر منه الغرباء‬
just for being related to such an idiot?!
‫فقط لأنّه سليل لذلك الغبيّ؟!‬
That's how I grew up!
‫هكذا كبرت أنا!‬
But... yeah.
‫ولكن... صحيح...‬
Over the past 400 years, many set sail to restore our family's honor,
‫خلال السنوات الأربعمئة الماضية‬ ‫أبحر العديد بهدف استعادة شرف عشيرتنا،‬
though all of them went missing.
‫ولقد فُقدوا جميعًا‬
I was ashamed of such a family.
‫شعرتُ بالخجل من هذه العائلة‬
I ran away from home and became a pirate.
‫هربتُ من المنزل وأصبحتُ قرصانًا‬
Oh? You're a pirate, too?
‫فعلًا؟ أنت قرصان أيضًا؟‬
It's not that I wanted to become a pirate.
‫ليس وكأنّني رغبتُ في أن أصبح قرصانًا‬
I just wanted to escape from Noland's curse.
‫أردت الهرب من لعنة نولاند فحسب‬
And over time, I put together my own pirate crew.
‫ومع الوقت، أصبح لي طاقم قراصنة خاصّ بي‬
At long last, I entered the Grand Line.
‫وبعد وقت طويل، دخلتُ الغراند لاين،‬
I spent all my time on adventures.
‫وكرّستُ كلّ وقتي للمغامرات‬
But ten years ago, my ship reached this island by accident.
‫لكن وصلت سفينتي لهذه الجزيرة بالصّدفة قبل عشر سنوات‬
I hated the Mont Blanc family and Noland more than anyone,
‫رغم كرهي لعائلة مونبلان ونولاند أكثر من غيري،‬
but strangely enough, I'm the only one that made it here.
‫كنتُ أنا وحدي من وصل إلى هنا وبشكل غريب‬
Just like the picture book said, this island didn't have a City of Gold.
‫لم تكن هنالك مدينة من الذّهب على الجزيرة كما ذُكر في الكتاب‬
As I stood on an island cape, it felt like destiny.
‫وبينما أنا واقف على رأس الجزيرة، شعرتُ أنّ هذا كان قدري‬
There was nowhere left to run.
‫ما عاد هنالك مكان للهرب‬
Let's settle this, Noland!
‫لننهِ هذا الأمر يا نولاند!‬
Hell no, Captain!
‫مستحيل! أيّها القبطان،‬
We want nothing to do with your family's problems!
‫ليس لدينا أيّ علاقة بمشكلات عشيرتك‬
If you insist on searching for the gold, do it alone!
‫إن أصررت على البحث عن الذّهب، فلك ذلك وحدك!‬
We're parting ways here. Farewell, Captain.
‫سنفترق هنا، وداعًا أيّها القبطان‬
If it's there, that's fine. If it's not there, that's fine, too.
‫لا بأس إن كانت هناك ولا بأس أيضًا إن لم تكن‬
It's not that I want to prove his innocence.
‫فلستُ أريد إثبات براءته‬
This is a duel with the man who screwed up my life.
‫هذا نزال مع الرّجل الّذي دمّر حياتي‬
Before I die, I want to set the record straight.
‫أريد أن أسوّي الأمر معه قبل أن أموت‬
What a man.
‫رجل ولا كلّ الرّجال‬
Then what about them? Why are those monkeys here?
‫إذًا ماذا عنهما؟ لماذا ذلكما القردان هنا؟‬
That must've also been an exciting drama
‫لا بدّ من وجود قصّة مثيرة‬
spoken with the fists of men committed to exploring the seabed!
‫حُبكت أحداثها بقبضات رجال كرّسوا حياتهم لاكتشاف الأعماق‬
They're fans of the picture book.
‫إنّهما مجرّد معجبين بكتاب الصّور‬
Fans?!
‫معجبان؟!‬
That's quite a simple connection.
‫إنّها علاقة بسيطة جدًّا‬
I think it was five or six years ago.
‫أعتقد أنّ ذلك كان قبل خمس أو ستّ سنوات‬
They heard a rumor about me and barged in.
‫سمعا إشاعة عنّي وأتيا إليّ‬
They said, "We think Noland's gold really exists!"
‫قالا «نعتقد أنّ ذهب نولاند موجود فعلًا»‬
Shojo!
‫شوجو!‬
You're going down after kicking me so suddenly!
‫هل أنت جاهز لمواجهتي بعد ركلك لي فجأة هكذا؟!‬
That's a wild accusation, Masira!
‫هذا اتّهام زائف شنيع يا ماسيرا!‬
Don't make me angry!
‫لا تغضبني!‬
The sea around here is deep.
‫البحر في هذه المنطقة عميق‬
In the dark and cold waters, you're haunted by a deeper solitude.
‫وفي البحر البارد المظلم، تطاردك وحدة أعمق بكثير‬
I simply dove and searched day by day on my own.
‫كنتُ أغوص وأبحث وحدي كلّ يوم‬
Then they barged into my life,
‫دخلا حياتي دون سابق إنذار‬
romping around and becoming my underlings without permission.
‫وأصبحا تابعين لي دون إذني، ولزما المكان هنا‬
Single-minded idiots like them...
‫إنّ غبيّين بسيطا الفهم مثلهما يشعرانني بالرّاحة بصراحة‬
Do you understand?
‫هل تفهمون؟‬
I do. Yeah, real comrades give each other strength and...
‫أنا أفهمك. إنّ الزّملاء الحقيقيّين يمنحون بعضهم القوّة و...‬
That's enough monkeying around.
‫حسنًا، كفانا حديثًا عن ذلكما القردين...‬
Then why even ask?! Just let him finish!
‫لا تسأل عنها من الأساس وأطبق فاهك!‬
Like I said, I wanna go to the sky island!
‫كما قلت، أريد الذّهاب إلى جزيرة السماء أيّها العمّ!‬
You're a hasty one!
‫أنت قليل الصّبر حقًّا!‬
Didn't I say the witness to the sky island is that Noland the Liar?
‫ألم أخبرك؟ الشاهد الوحيد لجزيرة السماء هو نولاند الكذّاب‬
If you have anything to do with him, you'll be laughed at like me.
‫إن أصبحت لك أيّ علاقة به، فسيضحك عليك الجميع مثلي‬
What?! He's been to the sky island, too?!
‫ماذا؟! هل زار جزيرة السماء أيضًا؟!‬
Unfortunately, this doesn't say he went there, but...
‫للأسف، لم يُذكر هنا أنّه فعل، ولكن...‬
A logbook?! Could it be Noland's?
‫سجلّ سفينة؟! أهو لنولاند؟!‬
That's right.
‫صحيح.‬
Read, starting there.
‫اقرئي من تلك الجزئية.‬
Amazing. A logbook from 400 years ago.
‫مذهل! سجلّ من أربعمئة سنة مضت‬
Year 1120 of the pelagic calendar, June 21st, clear skies.
‫«اليوم 21 يونيو 1120 من التقويم الفلكيّ البحريّ، الجوّ مشمس‬
We left a cheerful town named Villa.
‫غادرنا بلدة فيرا المبهجة‬
Per the log pose, we should be heading east-northeast from the port.
‫وإن تبعنا البوصلة المسجِّلة‬
We got a rare item from a merchant that we came across during the day.
‫اشتريتُ شيئًا نادرًا من بائع متجول عثرنا عليه خلال النّهار‬
It's a ski-like, one-person boat called a waver.
‫إنّه قارب متزلّج لشخص واحد يُدعى ويفر‬
It's a mysterious craft that can move on a still day by creating its own wind.
‫قارب غامض يولّد رياحًا ويتحرّك حتّى في الأيّام الّتي لا رياح فيها‬
It takes some effort to ride though. I never figured it out.
‫يبدو أنّه يجب أن تعتاد عليه حتّى تركبه، ولم أستطع ذلك‬
Right now, it's become the perfect toy for my crew.
‫والآن، أصبح اللّعبة المثاليّة لطاقمي‬
No way! What's this? I want it!
‫مستحيل! ما هذا؟ أريد واحدًا!‬
Forget it! Keep reading!
‫لا تهتمّي لذلك، واصلي القراءة!‬
It's powered by an item found only on the sky island.
‫إنّ مصدر قوّته هو منتج يوجد في جزيرة السماء،‬
I hear that many peculiar things like that exist in the sky.
‫وسمعتُ أنّ عدّة أشياء فريدة أخرى توجد في السماء‬
Speaking of the sky island,
‫وبالحديث عن جزيرة السماء، أراني أحد‬ ‫رفاقي المستكشفين سمكة سماء حيّة‬
I was surprised at how strange the fish looked.
‫تفاجأت لغرابة شكل السمكة‬
Sky fish?
‫سمكة سماء؟‬
To our ship, it's still an unknown area,
‫ما زالت منطقة مجهولة لسفينتنا،‬
but as a sailor, I'd like to go to the sea in the sky one day.
‫لكن بصفتي بحّارًا، كم أودّ الذّهاب لبحر السماء يومًا‬
Mont Blanc Noland.
‫.مونبلان نولاند»‬
He said "the sea in the sky"!
‫قال «البحر في السماء»!‬
It's just like Robin said!
‫كما قالت روبين تمامًا!‬
And it seems obvious that people knew about the sky island back then.
‫ويبدو أنّ جزيرة السماء كانت أمرًا عاديًّا للغاية للنّاس في الماضي!‬
So it really does exist!
‫إذًا فهي موجودة حقًّا!‬
Alright!
‫مرحى!‬
Hey, Boss! How are you feeling?!
‫أيّها العجوز! كيف تشعر؟!‬
Never better!
‫بأفضل حال!‬
Glad to hear it!
‫سررت بسماع هذا!‬
Boss, this bastard...
‫أيّها العجوز، هذا الوغد...‬
Shut up and listen. Do you like those guys?
‫اخرسا واستمعا لي، أيروق لكما هؤلاء؟‬
Why do you ask?
‫لماذا تسأل؟‬
It seems they're intent on going to the sky island at any cost.
‫يبدو أنّهم يريدون الذّهاب إلى جزيرة السماء بأيّ ثمن‬
Sky island... If they wanna go, there's only one way to get there.
‫جزيرة السماء...‬
If they try on their own, they'll be dead in a flash, Boss.
‫إن حاولوا من تلقاء أنفسهم فسيقتلون فورًا أيها العجوز!‬
Exactly, so why don't we give them a hand?
‫بالضبط، لذا لمَ لا نقدّم يد العون لهم؟‬